um hi hello everyone I'm quite excited
to be here and first I'd like just to
thank you organizers for putting
together such a great conference thanks
so much for the invite
I'd like to start by saying that I'm a
philosopher okay so bear with me I don't
have a lot of formal stuff that you like
this is also brand new research so I'm
testing the waters here and see if
there's something that I should carry on
doing or not so let me know all the
feedback is very welcome okay
so having said that let me start by just
um just saying that what I want what I
want to research here is a the impact of
action and I take a subjective
experience to be in the action okay so
the idea here is to look at our action
is what may or may not allow explaining
the neural connectivity in the brain
okay so the presentation will be the
five of in two parts our one
metaphysical the other one is
neuroanatomy so first what I'm going to
do is I'm going to look at the
fundamental distinction between the
metaphysics of inference between
functional and effective connectivity
this will then allow me to focus on
effective connectivity and I want to
look at particularly on the oculomotor
system as sort of a study case and I'm
going to look at that from the active
inference point of view okay so um yet
we all know are from the last three days
at least that the integration of the
brain areas is something that is quite
difficult to assess and one way to do
that is by looking to the in terms of
the brain connectivity and our cognition
integrates from that point of view which
is what motivates me to look at the
metaphysics of the connectivity so first
I want to just focus on the motivation
ok so the idea here is that there is
this oppression operational distinction
between functional and effective
connectivity and this is important
because
it allows us to determine the nature of
the inferences that can be made about
cognitive integration and also most
importantly the questions there one
should be asking and I'm following here
Tristan in doing so so what I want to do
is just look at the differentiation on
the one hand on the causal modeling in
effective connectivity and on the other
hand as it is opposed to the procedures
used to characterize functional
connectivity okay so let me start by
looking at functional connectivity just
the very basics the aim is that it is
inferred on the basis of temporal
correlations between time series of
different brain regions in a sort of
measurements of this modular neural
activity these connections are can then
be in the stood in terms of these causal
symmetry that is in terms of these
probabilities and temporal order okay so
the aim here and what is more important
is that the aim is like that to identify
which are the segregated brain regions
that are most likely to connect in order
to carry on a specialized kind of
function or for a task to main and I
think Han and colleagues are captured is
really well when they say that the
functional specialization and anatomical
segregation of neural networks in the
brain imply that it is organized as
distributed hierarchical network of
highly specialized networks of spiking
neurons so the idea is that there's this
time-resolved
functional connectivity which is claimed
as crucial to displaying a sort of a
balance between on the one hand
functional segregation and on the other
hand integration of brain networks and
here's where modularity networks comes
handy and particularly important because
it attempts to do just starts to find
the patterns of correlations between
functionally segregated areas on the one
hand
it's significant integration on the
other hand and that's where it becomes
quite important on the other hand we
have effective connectivity and here we
look at the causal dependency is more
like sort of what motivates the coupling
or the direct influence between for
example a and B this will rest obviously
is basically on a model of that
influence that is called a generative
model this kind of models the generative
models are then compared as the
probabilistic strategy is at the heart
of these analysis in effective
connectivity so following frist and it
tells us that effective connectivity
explains brains networks by virtue of
accounting for the dynamic activity
activity dependent and the dependence on
a model of these interactions one
example of these studies on effective
connectivity can be found for example in
Sokolove and colleagues when they look
at visual sensitivity to biological
motion that cause changes in the
connectivity and actually how this
active interaction relates to behavior
so this analysis of effective
connectivity it can be said that it is
both neural and activity lab and it is
on this account that these models are
conducted or carried by effective
connectivity are said to be quite
dynamic so the idea is that artists if
they do not suppose that there are there
is this invariant structure that can be
captured anatomically okay so um just
let me let us just have a look at how we
can just a systematize these differences
between functional and effective
connectivity which will allows that
allows allows me to then move forward to
effective connectivity okay on the one
hand we have effect of the from the
functional connectivity as being a sort
of identifying temporal correlations or
covariances
on the other hand effective connectivity
as a matter of explaining these causal
dependences we have also on functional
connectivity are the aim to map from
imaging data which is it's physiological
consequences to its diagnostic class
which is a categorical kind of cause on
the other hand we have an effective
connectivity sort of a model comparison
as with just saw generative models of
coupling among these hidden brain states
sorry on the other hand and effective
connectivity we have mapping from causes
to consequences so the other way around
so we have own functional connectivity a
sort of a predictive model whereas on
effective connectivity it's more of a
model comparison Jarett of model of
coupling among hidden brain states ok
good so some people think and come
forward to say that well effective
connectivity is more powerful and less
ambiguous ok and this would this would
be the idea also followed by free stem
2011 well it that when it tells us well
this is the case because it captures
both the topological pairwise
connections as well as direct causal
influences and we can see that in these
graphs in which on the first one the
structural causal modeling we can look
at the topological pairwise connections
and on the second one with the dynamic
causal model modelling we can see that
but we can also see the direct causal
influence so this is what motivates me
to now focus on the affective
connectivity and now we can explain that
by looking at the oculomotor system ok
so what makes the oculomotor system such
an interesting case is that it is a
distributed network composed by the
cerebral cortex basal ganglia and the
cerebellum and the idea here is that
neural messages from these regions that
combined to generate signals to the
extraocular musk muscles to move the
eyes so to show this kind of coupling
between perception or vision and
action I will and the causal
dependencies on this neural connection I
will first look at the neuroanatomy and
then I'm gonna look at the active
inference okay
so just a very basics I just want to
flesh out just the saccadic eye so we
have the dynamic integration of vision
in action why well because the action
takes the form of the saccadic eye
movements that is a series of these
discrete fixations and there are
interposed by rapid and rapid movements
so while we may select a new target for
fixation it is necessary to apply forces
that decelerate the eyes towards their
target so this is the very basics of it
now moving at how we could explain this
relation between perception and action
through active inference we can say that
well by forming hypotheses this saccades
can be deployed as experiments to
adjudicate among alternatives so
unpacking this a little bit objects in
the visual field become hypotheses or
explanations that take the form of
something like what would I see if I
looked there so Bayesian filtering
equations can be used and implemented to
planning as ever as inference which can
generate both saccadic and smooth
pursuit eye movements so importantly the
associated message passing will map
pretty well on to the known connectivity
in neuroanatomy of the brainstem which
obviously didn't end don't have time to
explain here okay so this is some the
main point is just that there are these
signals that are carried by each eye to
the brainstem and they can be classified
in two broad categories and this is what
what the main point that I want to
stress out here that's the X T receptive
and the proprioceptive so on the
acceptive as we all know we have the
visual signals to the optic nerve and
then on the proprioceptive level there
is this extra ocular muscles into
the oculomotor nerves which control the
angular man Angela position and velocity
of each eye okay so in other terms
visual signals are then generated
through an identity mapping from the
position of the eyes right so this means
that what the eye sees what I see
depends entirely on where they look this
becomes quite important because then
proprioceptive states are what comes to
ensure that these mapping from the
hidden States to two outcomes and the
result of these outcomes is that then is
the reception so vision is depending or
in a dependence in a probabilistic sense
on proprioception which is to say in
action so the idea is that vision is
dependent on action and action will be
what explains these visual connections
okay um this causality between action
and perception can be explained in terms
of the free energy principle which is
that living systems must minimize the
original free energy over time and this
minimization of the free energy through
action and perception is referred to as
active inference active inference and
very briefly is just this theory there
is a front derives from the principle
that living systems must minimize the
dispersion of this the state in order to
continue to exist in a sort of a
meaningful way and in order to do that
to find the things that are relevant to
their own existence so that they don't
die they draw these predictions about
the sensations that they will encounter
and actively sample them in them to
reduce these uncertainty or
mathematically the expected Bayesian
surprise okay um now this becomes a form
of what Thomas paw and quarry stone
called the active vision and this is the
bit that I'm very interested on on
working on and building from
so this is the idea that this activision
is a charity of process these filled
circles are what gives rise to the
sensory data and then we have on the
other hand the charity of model which is
the unfilled circles which proposes this
data is generated now an arrow
connecting two variables indicates that
the second variable is conditionally
dependent on the first and is what I'm
particularly interested because this
this means that eyes are conditionally
dependent on target fixation prediction
okay so this fictive locations then will
cause changes in position in the
generative model and which brings us to
conclude that then action is part of
these Jarett of process okay so then how
do we put all of this together well
these equations can be implemented by
passing messages between populations of
neurons sending messages here are
excitatory prediction errors while
descending messages are the inventory
predictions and it is this patterns that
characterizes what we know is a
predictive coding now we see on the
right hat on the left hand side here we
got equations that describe these kind
of gradient descent on variational
free-energy
neural message passing and on the on the
right side we have these equations
mapping to the scheme of this generative
model so what happens is that we have a
map of the influences between each
population with excitatory and
inhibitory connections okay good now
bringing these to an end and take a
message what I want to say and what I
want to research on building on this is
that well first I think there are few
quite relevant and important points to
take from here is not accept receptive
vision and proprioception emerge from a
single imperative which is to
contextualise
each other in the sense that they all
are reducing minimizing the free energy
ineffective conic connectivity
terms then what motivates the specific
establishment of certain synaptic
connections and visions is the active
exploration and this is the bit that I'm
quite interested of the world by
focusing on what appear as salient to a
member of a certain phenotype now in
other times this means that active
inference on active domain the active
dimension of vision is what explains
these visual connections so which means
now we're not just simply collecting or
picking out what we see in the world
there is an active dimension to it
now finally the effective connectivity
captures these essential what is
essential to the construction and
explanation of the our article process
in the visual world okay now coming to
the last slide as to future work I just
want to say that it would be quite
important and crucial I think to find
these links between network topology in
neural dynamics that can address the
empirical problem of how the brain
adapts in a dynamic and flexible way and
according to the demands of the
cognitive interaction with the
environment which I take to be the
subjective experience now this was not a
talk about subjective experience this
doesn't mean that I don't think that
there is such thing as subjective
experience I think there is it's
inaction and by the way I wrote a paper
on what it feels like to prove a
mathematical equation so but actually
these top was more about the role that
subjective experience plays in neural
connections or and also neural
deployment so the question that I think
is quite relevant to to work on future
research is how this subjective
experience acts on the ways that the
brain connects and reorganizes to
connect in cognitive terms so this is me
thank you very much for your attention
[Applause]